<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Frink | Language Perils]]></title>
  <link href="http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/blog/categories/frink/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-25T04:12:36+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Beskin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Frink's Interval Arithmetic for the Masses]]></title>
    <link href="http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/blog/2015-02-19-frinks-interval-arithmetic-for-the-masses.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-19T19:25:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/blog/frinks-interval-arithmetic-for-the-masses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In the [previous post](/blog/2015-01-08-hello-frink.html) about Frink, we explored how smoothly Frink handles units of measure. In this post, we will focus on another deeply integrated feature of Frink's: interval arithmetic. On Frink's [homepage](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/) this feature is described as magical. The aim of this post is to try and make sense of this statement. We will now give a quick rundown of interval arithmetic and then proceed to concrete examples. For a more detailed review of the subject, you can refer to [Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_arithmetic), or for a Frink-specific treatment, to the [interval arithmetic section](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/#IntervalArithmetic) in Frink's documentation. On with it.

<!-- more -->

## Interval arithmetic 101

In interval arithmetic, instead of using numbers, we use intervals. Specifically, we say that `[3, 5]` represents the set of numbers between `3` and `5`. Given some intervals, we can define the basic arithmetic operations on them:
```
[a, b] + [c, d] = [a + c, b + d]
[a, b] - [c, d] = [a - d, b - c]
[a, b] * [c, d] = [min(ac, ad, bc, bd), max(ac, ad, bc, bd)]
[a, b] / [c, d] = [min(a/c, a/d, b/c, b/d), max(a/c, a/d, b/c, b/d)]
```

Which should make intuitive sense if you squint hard enough. With (quite) a bit more thought, it is possible to define interval operations for more complicated functions, e.g. trigonometric functions. And that's exactly what Frink does; most of its mathematical functions transparently support (real) intervals, so one can write:
```
x = new interval[-1, 4]
y = new interval[6, 9]

x + y  // => [5, 13]
x - y  // => [-10, -2]
x * y  // => [-9, 36]
x / y  // => [-1/6 (approx. -0.16666666666666667), 2/3 (approx. 0.66666666666666667)]

x^2    // => [0, 16]
sin[x] // => [-0.8414709848079, 1]
```

(Note that Frink uses square brackets for function application/definition.)

Although the interval definition syntax is a bit verbose and likely to change later on, the usage is indeed transparent. That is, code written for regular values (like the code above) works with intervals without any modification. Also, as can be seen in the `x^2` and `sin` examples, applying a function to an interval is not as simple as applying the function to the interval's boundaries, but rather involves an actual analysis of the function's behavior on the given interval.

And that's all we'll need for the purposes of this post. With this rudimentary knowledge of interval arithmetic, we are now ready to try and flesh out the claim that interval arithmetic is magical.

## Interval hat-trick

Suppose I want to prepare a classic hat-trick: pull a rabbit out of a top hat. For this, I would obviously need both a top hat and a rabbit. The question is, how do I make sure that the hat fits the rabbit? I can't just order any hat, it has to be large enough to contain the rabbit.

<img class="right" src="/images/frink/rabbit_measure.png" width="256" height="392">

Since I know literally nothing about rabbits and their sizes, I will use the picture on the right, depicting a fairly typical rabbit, as a reference.

From this picture, we need to extract an estimate of the rabbit's size. Luckily, the rabbit holds, as they usually do, a pocket watch, and using the handy table from [this](http://www.kenrockwell.com/watches/pocket-watch-sizes.htm) site we have an estimate of the diameter of a typical pocket watch:
```
pocketWatch = new interval[1.0, 1.9] inch 
// [0.0254, 0.04826] m (length)
```

As you can see, intervals are integrated with units; we could also have written `new interval[1.0 inch, 1.9 inch]`, but this way is more concise.

Knowing the diameter of a pocket watch, we can draw a little "pocket watch scale" for the rabbit (on the same picture on the right). We are assuming that both the legs and the ears are foldable, so the measurement excludes this area. Looking at the picture, we can see that the rabbit is about 10.5 watches tall, and about 5 watches wide. Since I don't really know how squishy a real rabbit is, let's give both dimensions a bit of an error margin either way, so:
```
heightInWatches = new interval[10.5 - 1, 10.5 + 1]
widthInWatches = new interval[5 - 0.5, 5 + 0.5]
```

Combining with the size of a watch we have:
```
rabbitHeight = heightInWatches pocketWatch
// [0.2413, 0.55499] m (length)

rabbitWidth = widthInWatches pocketWatch
// [0.1143, 0.26543] m (length)
```

According to [Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rabbit), a rabbit's weight is:
```
rabbitWeight = new interval[0.4, 2] kg
```

Which means, assuming that a rabbit forms a perfect cylinder, that we can calculate the rabbit's mass density:
```
rabbitVolume = pi (rabbitWidth / 2)^2 * rabbitHeight
rabbitDensity = rabbitWeight / rabbitVolume

rabbitDensity -> "water"
// [0.013025216116065158404, 0.8077748579515481546] water
```
So rabbits float on water; definitely a useful thing to know next time you go out with your rabbit to the beach. (Also, by nothing but a total coincidence, the height that we estimated fits pretty well with the data given in Wikipedia.)

Under the same cylindrical rabbit assumption, the width of the rabbit can be taken as the width of the top hat we'll be using. From which we gather that a magician's head circumference should be:
```
magicianHead = pi rabbitWidth

magicianHead -> "cm"
// [35.90840403053133671, 83.387293804233881917] cm
```

Which according to the table [here](http://www.ubs.iastate.edu/hat_sizing_chart.html) makes the potential magician either a giant or an extraordinarily small infant.

Having done this exhaustive research, we are now ready to order a hat. Just need to figure out where one buys a top hat these days...

Okay, so what do we have here? Essentially, we just did a calculation with built-in error propagation; which in itself is quite nice (and probably useful), but as every poor-soul-of-an-undergraduate-physics-student-stuck-in-a-lab knows, error analysis is not that difficult, even without the support of special programming tools (although I'm sure that said student would show nothing but great appreciation for such a tool). So apart from the magical theme, we are yet to achieve any real magic here.

But we won't be giving up just yet.

## Interval plotting

One good use of interval arithmetic techniques is for plotting. An illustration of this can be found on a [demonstration page](http://futureboy.us/fsp/simplegraph.fsp), which generates ASCII plots for equations. As can be seen in the Frink [source](http://futureboy.us/fsp/highlight.fsp?f=simplegraph.fsp) for this page, the code that achieves this uses interval arithmetic and is quite compact.

Let's try to figure out how it works. Before we do that, we need something to compare to the interval arithmetic approach. Since Frink doesn't (yet) have any built-in plotting facilities, we will roll our own simplistic plotting solution. For this purpose, we can leverage Frink's graphics support (which is much more interesting than what I'll be showing here, see the [documentation](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/#Graphics) for the full story).

Without further ado, the naive plotting solution:
```
naivePlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps] :=
{
  g = new graphics
  g.drawRectSides[xMin, -yMin, xMax, -yMax] // a frame for the plot
  
  xStep = (xMax - xMin) / xSteps
  yStep = (yMax - yMin) / ySteps
  
  tolerance = 0.05

  multifor [x, y] = [xMin to xMax step xStep, yMin to yMax step yStep]
  {
      res = abs[lhs[x, y] - rhs[x, y]]
      if res < tolerance
        g.fillRectSize[x, -y, xStep, -yStep]
  }
  
  g.show[]
}
```

(the full source code for this and further snippets can be found in the [repository](https://github.com/ncreep/language_perils/tree/master/Frink/interval_arithmetic))

The code should be fairly readable even without much familiarity with Frink. We are defining a function (as denoted by `:=`). The function takes two function arguments, `lhs` and `rhs`, each representing a side of the equation we are about to plot, and a bunch of numbers for the `x`/`y` limits and steps. Note that the curly braces must be on a separate line; which, from my point of view, is the only truly evil feature of Frink I've seen so far.

On line 3, we are initializing a new graphics object; this is the container for our plot. As a first step, on line 4, we are drawing a frame for the plot (otherwise, Frink might clip empty regions around it). Relative to standard mathematical plotting, the graphics object's `y` axis is inverted, hence the minus signs on all `y` values.

Next, we need to step through the range of the plot; instead of using two nested loops, we are using a `multifor`, which combines multiple nested loops into a single construct. At every step, we are applying the `lhs` and `rhs` functions to the current `x`/`y` values and see whether they are close enough. If they are within the tolerance value, on line 15 we are drawing a filled rectangle to mark that position.

After exiting the loop, on line 18, we invoke the `show` method on the graphics object, which shows the result on the screen.

This is probably the crappiest plotting solution one could possibly write. The tolerance is abysmal, but since we are using a constant step, a smaller tolerance would take too many steps to achieve anything. As it is, even moderately spiky functions should throw the whole thing off. Nonetheless, this can actually plot something, and it's good enough for illustration purposes.

Let's put it to the test. The preloaded example on the [demonstration page](http://futureboy.us/fsp/simplegraph.fsp) plots the equation
```
x^2 + y^2 = 81 sin[x]^2
```

Which should result in a bunch of circles. Let's try to apply `naivePlot` to draw them. First, we'll define a pair of anonymous functions for the parts of the equation:

```
lhs = { |x, y| x^2 + y^2 }
rhs = { |x, y| 81 sin[x]^2 }
```

The `{ |x, y| ... }` syntax defines an anonymous function with two arguments. After setting the bounds and number of steps, we can create the plot:

```
xMin = -10
xMax = 10

yMin = -10
yMax = 10

xSteps = 300
ySteps = 300

naivePlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps]
```

And the result:
<img class="center" src="/images/frink/naive_e1_300.png">

Which is reminiscent of the circles pattern we should be getting, but not quite there. We can push up the number of steps:
```
naivePlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, 800, 800]
```

To obtain:
<img class="center" src="/images/frink/naive_e1_800.png">

Since the step size is getting smaller, the points we are drawing are tiny. But the circles are definitely visible.

Now we can proceed to the interval arithmetic variant. Here's the code:
```
intervalPlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps] :=
{
  g = new graphics
  g.drawRectSides[xMin, -yMin, xMax, -yMax] // a frame for the plot
  
  xStep = (xMax - xMin) / xSteps
  yStep = (yMax - yMin) / ySteps

  multifor [xx, yy] = [xMin to xMax step xStep, yMin to yMax step yStep]
  {
      x = new interval[xx, xx + xStep]
      y = new interval[yy, yy + yStep]
      
      if lhs[x, y] PEQ rhs[x, y] // doing interval comparison
        g.fillRectSize[xx, -yy, xStep, -yStep]
  }
  
  g.show[]
}
```

The structure of `intervalPlot` is quite similar to `naivePlot`. The key difference is that instead of applying `lhs` and `rhs` to numbers, we are applying them to intervals. Specifically, at each iteration, we are creating intervals corresponding to the numbers between the current `x`/`y` values and the next (lines 11-12). As mentioned above, Frink's support for intervals is transparent, so we can apply `lhs` and `rhs` to the intervals in the very same way as we did in `naivePlot`. But now, instead of using a tolerance value to compare the results, we are using the operator `PEQ`, which stands for "Possibly EQuals", i.e. it tests whether the compared intervals have some overlap. This is one of a number interval-specific operators defined in Frink (for the full list see the [documentation](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/#IntervalComparisonOperators)). 

In the context of plotting, `PEQ` is exactly what we need; given that interval arithmetic produces the right bounds, there is no way for our code to miss solutions to the equation. To make this point more clear, we can consider two single-variable functions, `f` and `g` (which for simplicity we assume to be continuous). In the previous section, it was natural to view intervals as values with an uncertainty or a measurement error. But there is another way to look at them: an interval simultaneously represents all values in its range. With this interpretation, the expression `f([3, 5])` is equivalent to sampling the function on the whole range of `[3, 5]`. That is, the interval `f([3, 5])` contains all values that `f` can take on the range `[3, 5]`. So the assertion that `f([3, 5]) PEQ g([3, 5]) == false` means that nowhere in the interval `[3, 5]` the functions `f` and `g` can be equal. That is, `PEQ` guarantees us that there is no solution to the equation `f = g` in this interval. The converse statement, `f([3, 5]) PEQ g([3, 5]) == true`, is not as strong, it only tells us that `[3, 5]` may contain a solution to the equation, but it is not guaranteed (thanks to [Alan Eliasen](https://twitter.com/aeliasen) for clarifying this point). In the code above we assume that the solution does indeed exist, and we mark it on the plot (which may yield false positives if the resulting intervals are not tight enough; but that's beyond the scope of this post). In this way, we can achieve (paraphrasing the comment [here](http://mrhonner.com/archives/11643#comment-3980)) a "step-perfect" plot - if a solution to the equation exists within a step, `PEQ` cannot miss it (which contrasts probabilistic sampling methods, like `naivePlot`, that can miss possible solutions). Since in `intervalPlot` we are covering the whole plot range with intervals, we should see all solutions to the equation within the range.

Okay, but that's all just theory, what we really need is proof, and what can better serve as a proof than a picture. For the code
```
intervalPlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, 300, 300]
```
we get:

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/interval_e1_300.png">

Which is a bit crude, since we are not making that many steps. We should remember though, that for the equivalent step size in the naive approach, we got almost nothing at all. Here, as promised, we are not missing any solutions in the whole range. It is possible to refine the plot by increasing the step size:
```
intervalPlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, 800, 800]
```
and yield:

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/interval_e1_800.png">

Which is quite amazing, since this solution is as simple to implement as the naive solution, but it doesn't require us to muck about with tolerance values and step sizes, the burden of heavy lifting is on the implementation of interval arithmetic.

All this power at my fingertips... Let's try to plot something more ambitious. For this, we'll define the following functions:

```
/* A Gaussian function in one dimension */
gaussian[a, x] := exp[-x^2 / a^2]

/* A 2d Gaussian centered at (x0, y0) */
gaussian2d[a, x, x0, y, y0] := gaussian[a, x - x0] gaussian[a, y - y0]

/* A sum of 2d Gaussians with peaks at different locations. 
 * `peaks` is a list of pairs designating the positions of the peaks. 
 */
gaussians[a, x, y, peaks] :=
{
  res = 0
  for [x0, y0] = peaks
  {
     res = res + gaussian2d[a, x, x0, y, y0]
  }

  return res
}

/* A 2d surface with bumps at integer locations. */
bumps[x, y] := cos[2 pi x] cos[2 pi y]
```

Which is just a bunch of different bumpy functions. The sides of the equation that we will be plotting now are:
```
lhs = { |x, y| bumps[x, y] }
rhs = { |x, y| 2 - gaussians[0.01, x, y, peaks[]] }
```

Where `peaks[]` is a list of pairs:
```
peaks[] := [[1, 1], [1, 2], [1, 3], [1, 4], [1, 5], [2, 4], [3, 3], [4, 4], [5, 1], [5, 2], [5, 3], [5, 4], [5, 5], 
            [7, 1], [7, 2], [7, 3], [7, 4], [7, 5], [8, 3], [8, 5], [9, 3], [9, 5], [10, 1], [10, 2], [10, 3], [10, 4], [10, 5], 
            [12, 1], [12, 2], [12, 3], [12, 4], [12, 5], [13, 1], [13, 5], [14, 1], [14, 3], [14, 5], [15, 1], [15, 2], [15, 3], [15, 5], 
            [17, 1], [17, 2], [17, 3], [17, 4], [17, 5],
            [19, 1], [19, 2], [19, 3], [19, 4], [19, 5], [20, 1], [20, 5], [21, 1], [21, 5]]
```

The exact details of the various functions are not that important, what's important is that both `lhs` and `rhs` can be evaluated on intervals, and so can be plotted by `intervalPlot`. But first, let's see what `naivePlot` can make of it:

```
xMin = 0
xMax = 23

yMin = 0
yMax = 6

xSteps = 50
ySteps = 50

naivePlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps]
```

Since this function takes longer to evaluate, I won't bother with a larger step. And the result:

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/naive_e2_50.png">

One would've thought that with all the fuss defining the functions above, we'd have something more interesting as a result, oh well...

Let's try `intervalPlot` with the same step:

```
intervalPlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps]
```

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/interval_e2_50.png">

Now that's magic!

Okay, okay, I know, it's a bit gimmicky. Also, you might be thinking that defining some pathological function and then comparing the performance of the interval arithmetic solution to the joke of a plotting function that I came up with doesn't really prove anything. And you'd be right, it is a somewhat inadequate comparison (though I would like to point out again how ridiculously simple `intervalPlot`'s implementation is). If only I had something more solid to compare to.

I'm sure that most would agree that [WolframAlpha](http://www.wolframalpha.com/) knows a thing or two about plotting. Let's see how it compares to `intervalPlot`. Though it would be a bit tedious to submit our complete functions to WolframAlpha, so we'll simplify a bit:

```
lhs = { |x, y| bumps[x, y] }
rhs = { |x, y| 2 - guassian2d[0.01, x, 1, y, 1] }

xMin = 0
xMax = 2

yMin = 0
yMax = 2

xSteps = 50
ySteps = 50
```

Which is essentially the same as before, except that on line 2 we're not using `peaks[]` anymore, but just a single peak. We can run
```
intervalPlot[lhs, rhs, xMin, xMax, yMin, yMax, xSteps, ySteps]
```

and get:

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/interval_e3_50.png">

As of writing, [running the equivalent expression](http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=ContourPlot%5BCos%5B2+Pi+x%5D+Cos%5B2+Pi+y%5D+%3D%3D+2+-+Exp%5B-%28x+-+1%29^2%2F%280.01%29^2%5D+Exp%5B-%28y+-+1%29^2%2F%280.01%29^2%5D%2C+{x%2C+0%2C+2}%2C+{y%2C0%2C+2}%5D) on WolframAlpha yields the following:

<img class="center" src="/images/frink/wolfram_alpha_e3.png" width="320" height="320">

Although I've no idea how Mathematica (and by extension WolframAlpha) implements plotting for this sort of thing, I'm sure that it's not anywhere nearly as simple as our toy interval arithmetic function.

(Ironically, for the data above, `naivePlot` actually produces a plot with a point in the middle; but that's not really a meaningful result, but rather a coincidence, since even a minor tweak, e.g. `xSteps = 51`, makes the point disappear. `intervalPlot`, is, obviously, insensitive to such tweaks.)

Having said all that, I'm not actually knowledgeable enough to be actively recommending interval arithmetic plotting solutions as a drop-in replacements for anything else. As in any other non-trivial numerical problem, I'm sure that this area has its own set of nuances, which were not apparent in the examples used in this post. Probably, the best approach to plotting is some combination of various techniques. But still, I find it quite intriguing that we managed to get so far with such a small investment.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello Frink]]></title>
    <link href="http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/blog/2015-01-08-hello-frink.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-08T16:54:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ncreep.github.io/language_perils/blog/hello-frink</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, I'll be introducing the [Frink](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/) programming language. As stated on Frink's homepage:

>Frink is a practical calculating tool and programming language designed to make physical calculations simple, to help ensure that answers come out right, and to make a tool that's really useful in the real world. It tracks units of measure (feet, meters, kilograms, watts, etc.) through all calculations, allowing you to mix units of measure transparently, and helps you easily verify that your answers make sense. It also contains a large data file of physical quantities, freeing you from having to look them up, and freeing you to make effortless calculations without getting bogged down in the mechanics.

So Frink's "killer feature" is that you can write something like:
```
12.5 kilotons TNT / (6 years + 9 months) -> horsepower
// 329.48048477017130757
```

<!-- more -->

Although Frink is a full-featured programming language, including some support for object-oriented and functional programming, in this introductory post we'll be focusing only on Frink's ability to handle units. Since Frink's syntax should be pretty intuitive to anyone coming from the world of C-like languages, in future posts about Frink, I'll introduce new syntax as it comes up. (For some distant future readers living in a world where C-like syntax is long forgotten and Javascript is buried in the unreachable depths of the Internet Archive, if you haven't got a clue what I'm on about, I envy you.)

First things first, anything Frink related, including documentation and an interpreter, can be found on its [homepage](https://futureboy.us/frinkdocs/). Simple calculations can be run directly on the [web interface](https://futureboy.us/fsp/frink.fsp). Having set up a working environment (note that Frink is very frequently updated, hopefully, the code written here won't get dated too soon), we can move on to the premises of our exploratory session.

*<u>Clarification</u>: the author of the text below is not completely out of his mind, despite evidence to the contrary.*

Without further ado, the premises: we'll be trying to come up with a totally scientific method of making money ("...using this one weird trick discovered by a mad scientist..."), lots and lots of shiny money. I'll outline the revenue-generating method, and we'll use Frink to perform back-of-the-proverbial-napkin calculations to see how profitable it is (where, in our case, the "napkin" includes a computer and an internet connection). There will be some code soon, bear with me.

It's common practice to make money from currency exchange, which can be thought of as taking advantage of geography to make money. Looking at it from a slightly different angle, we are using some form of spatial relationships to generate profit. Since in physics there isn't much difference between space and time, why can't we use temporal relationships to earn money? "Ah", you might say, "he must mean stock trading". But no, that's too well-trodden a path to take, and it's not that interesting anyways. What I propose is to use time travel, specifically, time travel to the past, to generate profit. A naive approach might include using current stock market information to make money in the past, but I don't consider it to be a viable approach, since if you're too successful you're likely to get caught and be sent to jail for insider trading or something; and that's not cool at all. Another method would be to go to the past with a bunch of current dollars, and use the dollars' increased buying ability in the past to import some goods into the future. But using money from the future might raise suspicion as well. So we'll use a more subtle approach.

The method relies on the fact that prices of various goods vary differently over time. As a reference for historical prices, we'll use this table (adapted from [here](http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0873707.html), all prices are given in dollars):

<pre>
| Year | Bread (lbs) | Potatoes (10 lbs) |
|------|-------------|-------------------|
| 2010 | 1.41        | 5.79              |
| 1920 | 0.115       | 0.630             |
</pre>

So to make money, we can do the following:

* For `$5.79`, buy `10` pounds of potatoes today (which, according to the table, is 2010, but that's beside the point)
* Go back to 1920 and sell the potatoes for `$0.63`
* Buy `0.63 / 0.115 = 5.47` pounds of bread
* Return to the present and sell our bread for `$7.7`

Having executed this simple procedure, we just made a hefty profit of `7.7 - 5.79 = 1.91` dollars.

Of course, nothing is that simple, we should further explore this scenario.
For starters, we should convert our table into some Frink code. We could write something like:

```
breadNow = 1.41
bread1920 = 0.115

potatoesNow = 5.79
potatoes1920 = 0.630

// there are more civilized methods to import external data into Frink
// but that'll do for now
```

You might note that these are just plain numbers; given how Frink is all about the physical units, we should probably give these numbers some concrete units. We could use the units actually provided in the table, but as someone once said:
> If God had wanted us to use the metric system, he would have given us 10 fingers and 10 toes

(Though the distinguished scientist Frink, who lent his name to the Frink language, actually has 8 fingers, not sure what that implies...)

Luckily, unit conversion is deeply ingrained into Frink. Let's start with bread - the units implied by the table are dollar per lbs, writing this down in the interpreter gives us:
```
dollar / lbs
// 100000000/45359237 (approx. 2.2046226218487758) kg^-1 dollar (price_per_mass)
```

So no need for conversions, MKS is the (very sane) default. We can write down the rest of the values in the same manner:
```
// Frink recognizes juxtaposition as multiplication

breadNow = 1.41 dollar / lbs
bread1920 = 0.115 dollar / lbs

potatoesNow = 5.79 dollar / (10 lbs)
potatoes1920 = 0.630 dollar / (10 lbs)
```

And now we have all of our data with proper units. We can describe our money making scheme using Frink, though we'll be trying to rake in more profit now:
```
moneyInvested = tonne potatoesNow
// 1276.4764980504411924 dollar (currency)

moneyFromPotatoes = tonne potatoes1920
// 138.89122517647287585 dollar (currency)

breadBought = moneyFromPotatoes / bread1920
// 547.82608695652173911 kg (mass)

moneyFromBread = breadBought breadNow
// 1702.9271956419717822 dollar (currency)

moneyMade = moneyFromBread - moneyInvested
// 426.4506975915305898 dollar (currency)
```

Ha, it works! We've just made ourselves about 430 dollars, and all it took is to buy a mere tonne of potatoes. Well almost, I'm ignoring the fact that we actually don't have a time machine. Speaking of which, though I've little experience with actual time travel, I would imagine that, just like in space travel, in a real time machine (and not those made-up ones you see in the movies) the allowed weight and volume on a mission would be seriously constrained.

We know how much weight we'll be carrying, but how much volume would that make? Simple enough, we just need the densities of bread and potatoes, which can be found, for example, [here](http://www.fao.org/docrep/017/ap815e/ap815e.pdf):
```
bread = 0.29 g / ml
potato = 0.59 g / ml
```

And so:
```
548 kg / bread // 1.8896551724137931034 m^3 (volume)
tonne / potato // 1.6949152542372881356 m^3 (volume)
```
From which we can conclude that bread is the constraining element here. But these numbers are a bit meaningless; we need to compare them to something familiar. An average fridge is about 20 cubic feet, converting manually is simple enough (I'm using weird American units just to show that Frink doesn't scare easily):
```
(548 kg / bread) / (20 cubic feet)
// 3.3366271316165081822
```

But we don't actually need to bother with manual unit conversion, since Frink has a nifty unit conversion operator: `->`. For example, we can write:
```
1.67 meter -> feet 
// 5.4790026246719160105
```

Adding quotes on the right-hand side gives a bit of nice formatting:
```
1.67 meter -> "feet" 
// 5.4790026246719160105 feet
```

Note that the result is a string value and not a number.

What's even nicer is that the right-hand side can contain an arbitrary numeric expression with compatible units, so we are not limited to just built-in units. Back to our example, we can write it as:

```
548 kg / bread -> 20 cubic feet
// 3.3366271316165081822
```

We can also define our own custom unit for fridge related measurements (which come up quite often, so definitely a worthwhile investment) and have:
```
fridge = 20 cubic feet

548 kg / bread -> "fridge"
// 3.3366271316165081822 fridge
```

Making our 430 dollars would require us to carry 3 fridges full of bread, from 90 years back in the past. Fair enough, nothing comes for free; making a bit of an effort for money builds character, or something.

Let's get more ambitious, we can arrange our retirement with a big score of 1 million dollars (and when I say "our", I mean "my", since it's my plan, I'm just thinking out loud here). Rearranging the equations from the previous excursion to the past, we have:
```
potatoesToBuy = 1 million dollar / (potatoes1920 breadNow / bread1920 - potatoesNow)
potatoesToBuy ->  "tonne"
// 2344.9369543717689376 tonne
```

Whoa, that's a lot of potatoes, let's see how many fridges we'll need:
```
potatoesToBuy / potato -> "fridge"
// 7017.8531378425014657 fridge
```

And it gets worse with the bread we'll have to carry back from the past:
```
breadVolume = potatoesToBuy potatoes1920 / bread1920 / bread
breadVolume -> "fridge"
// 7821.6971854154656513 fridge
```

At these volumes, fridges become a bit meaningless as well; I, personally, have never seen so many fridges in one place (if you did, you can share this bizarre experience in the comments). A [space shuttle fuel tank](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_Shuttle_external_tank) is about 2.6 million liters:
```
spaceFuelTank = 2.6 million liters

breadVolume -> "spaceFuelTank"
// 1.7037369176037532356 spaceFuelTank
```

Hmm, 2 space shuttle fuel tanks, that's a lot. Makes me wonder... If a human can be "fueled" by bread or potatoes, can we fuel a space shuttle with them?

```
// food calories, as apposed to regular calories, are written with a capital 'C'
breadCalories = 260 Calories / (100 gram)
potatoCalories = 80 Calories / (100 gram)

// rocket fuel
liquidH2 = 8.5 MJ / L

fullFuelTank = liquidH2 spaceFuelTank

bread breadCalories spaceFuelTank -> "fullFuelTank"
// 0.37139378823529411764 fullFuelTank

potato potatoCalories spaceFuelTank -> "fullFuelTank"
// 0.23249054117647058823 fullFuelTank
```

Not bad, of the two, bread seems to be the better alternative to rocket fuel; although we'll need more than two tanks of bread to compensate for its inefficiency (this is not, hmm, quite accurate, since in an actual fuel tank, not all volume is taken by liquid hydrogen, but, whatever). I won't take any responsibility for the consequences of actually trying to send a space mission on pure bread fuel; I am willing to take credit if it works out, though.

Anyways, we got a bit sidetracked by a somewhat ridiculous idea - back to our more serious business plans. So making one big score and retiring doesn't seem to be in our cards. We'll probably have to devise some working schedule and move our goods in batches; time travel can really become a 9-to-5 job. But still, for now, it's a niche market, I'm sure that profit is guaranteed.

Since it's a 9-to-5 job, we can try to figure out what our daily commute would be like. Judging by various movies, it seems that time travel is nearly instantaneous, but that's ridiculous, one's daily commute can't be that fast (I'm sure there's a law of physics that governs that). I propose a more reasonable rate of half an hour per one year traveled into the past. So traveling ninety years back takes:
```
ninety years (half hour / year) -> "hours"
// 45.0 hours
```

That's quite the commute, but we're aiming for much profit, so that's how it is. 

One small wrinkle though, in the calculations above, we didn't account for the monetary investment in actual time travel. Let's sort this out. For the present discussion, I'll ignore the one-time investment of actually obtaining a time machine; as it's just a minor technical detail, a bit of research and engineering should settle it. Given that we are probably going to make many time trips, I would like to have an estimate of how much a single trip actually costs.

In physics, when one goes between time and space values, one uses the speed of light (`c`) as a conversion factor. We're going to stretch this analogy (till it utterly bursts) to provide some estimates for the energy consumption of a time trip. 

Since we are not actually moving, I think it's reasonable to assume that time travel doesn't have any friction (like air friction when flying). If one day someone discovers some kind of "time friction", we'll have to modify our calculations accordingly. But for now, ignoring friction, we can estimate the energy consumption of our trip just by knowing the difference in the required "velocities". The starting point is that we are moving forwards in time at a rate of one second per second. What we want to achieve, is a movement backwards in time one year per half hour, and of course, we need not forget to convert everything to velocity values using the speed of light:
```
startVelocity = c second / second
targetVelocity = -c year / (half hour)
```

We can plug our "velocities" into the formula for kinetic energy (`m/2 v^2`) and take the difference for our energy consumption. Assuming that the payload is a tonne of potatoes, we have:
```
timeTravelEnergy = tonne/2 (targetVelocity^2 - startVelocity^2)
// 1.3811974908674380205e+28 m^2 s^-2 kg (energy)
```

Which is the energy we need to invest to accelerate back in time. We could similarly ballpark the return trip, but that `e+28` in the result looks really suspicious. Let's try to see what it means:
```
// the atomic bomb dropped on Hiroshima
littleBoy = 15 kilotons TNT

timeTravelEnergy -> "littleBoy"
// 2.1992890208392057905e+14 littleBoy

// not even close...

// a hydrogen bomb, the most powerful nuclear weapon ever detonated
tsarBomba = 50 megatons TNT

timeTravelEnergy -> "tsarBomba"
// 6.5978670625176173713e+10 tsarBomba

// nope

// world energy consumption in the years 1980 - 2012
worldEnergyConsumption = 12676 quadrillion Btu

timeTravelEnergy -> "worldEnergyConsumption"
// 1.0327568857509895368e+6 worldEnergyConsumption

// nah ah

// the asteroid that killed the dinosaurs
chicxulubImpact = 100 teratons TNT

timeTravelEnergy -> "chicxulubImpact"
// 32989.335312588086856 chicxulubImpact

// getting warmer (pun intended)...

energyToEvaporateAllOceans = 3 octillion joules

timeTravelEnergy -> "energyToEvaporateAllOceans"
// 4.6039916362247934016 energyToEvaporateAllOceans
```
(the figures above come from [a](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Boy) [number](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsar_Bomba) [of](http://www.eia.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/IEDIndex3.cfm?tid=44&pid=44&aid=2) [various](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicxulub_crater) [sources](http://scientificlogic.blogspot.co.il/2010/04/how-much-heat-is-needed-to-vaporize.html))

Got it! So all we need to power our little business trip is the energy equivalent of evaporating all oceans on Earth, five times. Right. So how does *that* affect our revenue? Assuming we'll be using rocket fuel for our travels:

```
liquidH2Price = 3 dollar / kg
liquidH2SpecificEnergy = 142 MJ / kg

requiredFuel = timeTravelEnergy / liquidH2SpecificEnergy

fuelMoney = requiredFuel liquidH2Price

totalRevenue = moneyMade - fuelMoney
// -2.9180228680297986306e+20 dollar (currency)
```

Well, that sucked...]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
